This point, I've logged in to Qwiklabs, I've started the lab and
今回はQwiklabsにログインして ラボを開始します
I now have a username and password and using that I've logged in to the GCP
自分のユーザー名とパスワードで GCP Consoleにログインします
console, I've started data lab and I have data lab running.
Datalabを開始して動作させます
So the first thing that I'm going to do is I need to clone the repository in which
最初にすべてのノートブックがある リポジトリのクローンを作成します
So, an easy way to do that, one way to do that is to use the git icon up here but
上のGitアイコンを使うと簡単ですが
another way to do this to just go ahead and
新しいノートブックを作成して bash機能を使う方法もあります
So, I can basically say bash and git clone the,
では「bash git clone」と 入力していきます
So at this point, I'm git cloning the training data analyst
training-data-analystリポジトリを git cloneします
repository that contains the notebook that we want to use for this lab.
このラボで使いたいノートブックが 含まれています
And now if we go here,
ここに先ほどのtraining-data-analystがあります
So we'll go into training data analyst, go to the folder that
training-data-analystに入って フォルダに移動します
contains the notebook, so deep dive and
ノートブックが入っているので確認します
we're in the third course and we're looking at cloud ML engine.
3番目のコースでCloud ML Engineを確認します
So here's cloud ML engine and what we're doing in this lab is that we're
これがCloud ML Engineです このラボでは
essentially scaling up our transfer flow model.
TensorFlowモデルをスケールアップします
The same model that we had except that we've made it now a python model and
すでに作ったモデルと同じですが 今度はPythonモデルで作り
we're going to be running it on ML Engine.
ML Engineで実行します
So the first thing to do is that because we're going to be running it on the cloud,
クラウドで実行するので 最初に
So we will use that project ID as the project that is going to get built and
このプロジェクトIDを プロジェクトの作成に使用します
the bucket, what is a bucket?
そしてバケットです バケットとは何でしょうか？
We need to create a bucket, so one thing that we can do is to go into
バケットを作成しなければなりません
And check if there's a bucket already that exists, if not, we will create one.
バケットがあるか確認して なければ作成します
Bucket names have to be unique and so how do we get a unique bucket?
バケットの名前は一意にしてください それにはどうすればいいでしょうか？
One way is to use a bucket name that is the same name of the project and
1つの方法として バケット名をプロジェクトと同じ名前にします
unless we are extremely unlucky, someone hasn't created a bucket with this name.
よほど運が悪くなければ この名前のバケットは作成されていません
So I'll go ahead and
バケットの名前を作成し マルチリージョンバケットを作成できます
And, go ahead and create the bucket, and at this point, the bucket exists.
ここでバケットができました
The bucket is the same name as the project, so that makes it quite easy.
バケットはプロジェクトと同じ名前なので とても簡単です
I will go ahead, and
それから
in where the bucket is needed, I'll specify the bucket name and the region.
バケットが必要になったら バケット名とリージョンを指定します
Now, the region is extremely important,
リージョンはとても重要です
the region is a region in which you're going to be submitting your ML engine job.
リージョンとはML Engineジョブの送信先です
If you had a single region bucket,
単一リージョンのバケットを 使っていた場合は
you will want your computer to be in that same region.
同じリージョンに指定したいでしょう
Ours is a multi region bucket, so it doesn't really matter,
これはマルチリージョンのバケットですが どちらでもかまいません
we can use whichever region that we want to do our compute in so
コンピューティングに 使いたいリージョンを使えるので
I will leave it as US central.
us-centralのままにします
That happens to be the same region that I started data lab in but
これはDatalabを始めたときと 同じリージョンですが
there is no necessity that the data lab instance and the ML engine jobs have to
DatalabインスタンスとML Engineジョブは
run in the same region, they could run in different regions.
別のリージョンでも実行できます
All that we're doing is, we're submitting a job and all of the machines that they're
ここではジョブ送信と ジョブ実行のために作成するマシンは
going to create to run the job are going to be in the region US central one.
すべてus-central1にします
So I can save the notebook to make sure I don't lose it,
ノートブックを保存しておきます
so there's my project and one way to is to basically go ahead and click run.
私のプロジェクトで[Run]をクリックします
From now on I'll just do shift enter and that's essentially running it as well.
今度からはShift+Enterを押します これでも動作します
So this creates a project bucket and region variables and python.
これでPROJECT、BUCKET、REGIONの変数が Pythonで作成されます
The next cell essentially sets that the same exact variables but in bash.
次のセルは同じ変数を設定します ただしbashです
So we're doing os.environ, that's a Python command that sets a bash variable.
Pythonのコマンドos.environで bashの変数を設定します
So at this point now, anytime in the notebook we do dollar project or
これで ノートブックで$PROJECTや
dollar bucket, we will get the appropriate variable in the bash script.
$BUCKETを使えば bashスクリプトで該当する変数が取得できます
And so we're essentially using that here, we're saying GCloud can fake,
ここでやっていることは gcloudはフェイクが使えるので
set the project to be this project that they've set and
プロジェクトが設定済みの このプロジェクトだと設定し
set the compute region to be this region that we have set.
コンピューティングリージョンも 設定済みのリージョンだと設定します
So at this point, it has updated the core project and the compute region.
コアプロジェクトとコンピューティング リージョンが 更新されました
Now one thing is, Cloud ML Engine actually runs in a shadow project, and
ここでCloud ML Engineは シャドウプロジェクトで動作し
we want to basically provide access to all of our data files to ML engine.
次に全データファイルへのアクセス権を ML Engineに付与します
ML engine is not us, ML engine is a robot account, it's an automated account.
ML Engineは人間ではなく 自動化ロボットアカウントです
It's a service account and we want to give that service account access
サービスアカウントであり このサービスアカウントに
to be able to read files in our bucket so that's what this is doing.
バケット内のファイルへの 読み取り権限を付与します
It's basically saying, go ahead and
つまりここでは
give ML engine access to any files that are existing in the bucket and to new
ML Engineにバケット内の 既存のファイルと
Because we're going to be storing things like checkpoint and
このバケットにチェックポイントや
model output in that bucket as well, so that's exactly what you're doing.
モデルの出力なども格納するからです
essential data in the bucket so that ML engine can have access to it, can read it.
ML Engineがアクセスして読み取れるデータです
So typically,
通常はすべてのデータを保存するバケットは 作成しません
You want to create buckets that are specific for machine learning and
機械学習固有のバケットを作成し
keep just those files in there, it helps keep your security more constraint.
そのファイルだけを保存すると セキュリティを向上できます
So we're going to do that, and
ここで
we're going to give ML engine access to read and write into this bucket.
ML Engineにこのバケットへの 読み書き権限を付与します
And then, once that's done, so at this point what that's done is it's authorized
付与したらML Engineサービスアカウントを 承認します
the ML engine service account, the service account is essentially a service hyphen.
アカウントはservice-の後に
This is the project ID and
プロジェクトIDです
you can find the project ID by going into the GCP console.
プロジェクトIDを見つけるには GCP Consoleに移動します
If you go into the home, there is a project ID in here,
[Home]に移動するとプロジェクトIDがあります
project number here, that is the same project number.
プロジェクト番号はここです 同じプロジェクト番号です
But you don't need to know this, we can script it in such a way that we can
これは覚えなくてかまいません
get it and the way we're scripting it is to basically go ahead and
スクリプトで取得できます
And having done that, next thing to do is that we have to take our code,
次はコードを取り出します
the earlier labs our code was in a notebook,
コードは前のラボの実験で ノートブックに書いたからです
We're building things, but now we want to run it at scale and
今回は大規模実行するので コードを送信して実行したいときは
that code will be in a Python package, so that's what we're doing here.
Pythonパッケージにします
We are creating a Python package and the Python package,
Pythonパッケージを作成します
I'm calling it taxifare, and it contains all of these files.
パッケージtaxifareにこのファイルすべてを入れます
You can look at them in data lab, by going into data lab, and if you look inside
Datalabで確認できます
and trainer contains the two files that we talked about in the slides.
trainerには2つのファイルがあります
Task.py and model.py, task.py is the one that contains main,
task.pyとmodel.pyです
it basically does all of the command line per sync and it basically looks for
同期のたびにコマンドラインをすべて読み
That come in from the command line and model.py contains a core of the model.
これはコマンドラインから来ます
This is what basically creates appropriate regressure,
これは適切なリグレッサーを作成し
it has the input functions to read the data, etc.
データを読み取る入力関数などがあります
And so, at this point, we have our package and the package in Python
ここにパッケージがあります Pythonのパッケージは
is essentially just a folder structure that has all of these files that we need.
必要なファイルがすべて含まれる フォルダ構造です
And we can go ahead and look at model.py, and
ではmodel.pyを確認しましょう
this is essentially all the code that was in the data lab notebooks before
これは基本的に 以前Datalabの ノートブックにあったコードで
that we are now essentially putting into a Python package.
これをPythonパッケージにします
So, one question that we get is how do you take Python code and
ここで問題は どうやってPythonコードを取り出して
put it into a Python package?
パッケージにするかです
One easy way to do this, so let's look for something that has Python.
1つ簡単な方法があります Pythonが書かれたものを見てみましょう
So let's say this is the code that we want to write into a file,
このコードをファイルに書き込みます
one easy way to do this is to use Jupiter Magic called write file.
簡単なのはJupyter Magicの writefileを使うことです
I can say writefile tensorboard.py and
writefile tensorboard.pyと入力して 実行すると
when I execute this, all of the code in here will get written into tensorboard.py.
ここにあるコードが すべてtensorboard.pyに書き込まれます
So that is an easy way that you can take code that's in the Python notebook,
このように簡単に Pythonノートブックのコードを取得して
and write it out into a separate Python file into a Python package.
別のPythonファイルに書き出して Pythonパッケージに入れられます
Writefile also has the option to append, so
writefileは追加のためのオプションもあり
you can actually add extra lines if you wanted, to python.py.
必要に応じてPython .pyに 行を追加できます
So I'll just remove this because we actually want to run it, but
これは削除します
to show you that tensorboard.py actually got written,
書き込まれたtensorboard.pyを見るため
we can go back into the directory and
ディレクトリに戻りましょう
in 03_tensorflow you should see a tensorboard.py.
03_tensorflowにtensorboard.pyがあります
So this was essentially the file that got written by me writing
これが%writefileで書き出したファイルです
So we have at this point, created a Python package, and
ここではPythonパッケージを作成して
we can essentially make sure that we have our data files.
データファイルがあることを確認できます
Here's the data file, everything in data lab is mapped to slash content,
これがデータファイルで Datalabのすべてが/contentにマップされ
so that is the directory that it's at.
このディレクトリに入っています
And we basically printed out one line of the training input file and
トレーニングの入力ファイルの1行と
one line of the validation input file.
検証入力ファイルの1行を出力しています
And now I have a Python package, one good idea is to always try to run it,
Pythonパッケージがあるので 実行してみましょう
run the Python package, it has nothing to do with ML engine.
Pythonパッケージの実行は ML Engineと関係ありません
You have a Python package and you want to run it and the way you run a Python
Pythonパッケージを実行するには
package is to basically go python-m, passing in the module.
python -mにモジュールを渡します
The name of the module is task, it's in the package trainer but
モジュール名はtaskですが trainerパッケージにあるので
in order to do that we have to tell Python where to find it and
Pythonが探す場所を PYTHONPATHで設定します
And you set it to be the current directory/taxifare,
それを現在のディレクトリの /taxifareに設定します
because that's where trainer was, so, I specify the PYTHONPATH and
ここにtrainerがあるからです PYTHONPATHを指定して
I run the Python program, passing in taxi-traine, passing in taxi-valid.
pythonプログラムに taxi-train*とtaxi-validを渡して実行します
So making sure that these command line paths work as intended, specifying
このコマンドラインパスが正しいことを 確認します
an output directory, and specifying a small number of training steps.
出力ディレクトリと 少数のトレーニング手順を指定します
I could specify even just ten steps if I wanted, and
手順10個だけでも指定できます
now I can basically run it by hitting shift enter.
これでShift+Enterで実行できます
And at this point, that Python module is getting run and
ここでPythonモジュールを実行して
we make sure that it works, and once it works,
動くことを確認します 動いたら
we can make sure that we can check that something actually did get written out.
何が書き出されたかを確認できます
So the whole thing gets run, and
全部実行されて
you noticed that a saved model got written up, that is a key thing.
保存されたモデルに書き込まれました これが重要です
We want to make sure, that the training happened and
トレーニングが行われて
we got a saved model, and we can check this
保存されたモデルがあることを確認します
by looking inside export/exporter to make sure that the saved model exist.
それにはexport/exporterに保存されたモデルが 存在することを確認します
So it exist in that directory and one of the things that we can do,
このディレクトリに存在しています
is that we can try to make sure that everything works, not so
ここで すべて動作するか確認できます
this point I have not done ML engine at all, I'm still running inside data lab.
ML Engineはまったく実行していません まだDatalabの中で実行しています
I'm checking to make sure that the python module works,
確認しているのはPythonモジュールの動作です
that I have a tested JSON, notice that I'm using the writefile here,
test.jsonにここで使ったwritefileで
though essentially write this line as test.json.
この行を書き込みます
And then, using the gcloud command,
gcloudコマンドを使って
with the local directory that's being exported, and I'm passing in
ローカルディレクトリをエクスポート先にして
the test.json to make sure that the exporting works that the predictions work.
test.jsonを渡し エクスポートが動作し 予測が動作することを確認します
And this whole sequence here works as a Python module, just running locally.
このシーケンス全体がPythonモジュールとして ローカルで動作します
The prediction is not going to be very accurate, I just trained for 10 steps but
予測はあまり正確ではありません 10の手順でしかトレーニングしていません
we know that all the code works, that we have trained the model, we have exported
ただしコードは全部動作します モデルをトレーニングしてエクスポートし
it and we're able pass an adjacent input and we're able to predict with it.
JSON入力を渡し それを使って予測できます
And at that point, we can also, if we wanted,
ここでgcloud ml-engineを使って
train locally using GCloud ML engine,
ローカルでトレーニングできます
this is exactly the same as doing python-m.
python -mとまったく同じです
The difference here is that we specify the module name and
ただモジュール名とパッケージのパスの指定が
the package path in a slightly different way and,
少し違うくらいです
we don't need to specify a python path because ML engine knows how to do that.
Pythonのパス指定は不要です ML Engineが知っているからです
And, we can specify all of those parameters
これらのパラメータをすべて指定すると
that our model actually it takes.
モデルが受け取ります
Once we do that, regardless of how you do it, whether you use it with GCloud or you
その後 gcloudとpython -mの どちらを使った場合でも
use it with python-m, you can basically run tensor board to visualize the model.
TensorBoardを実行して モデルを可視化できます
So I'll go ahead and start tensor board, okay, it should be here.
ではTensorBoardを開始しましょう ここにあります
We want to pass in the current directory.
現在のディレクトリを渡します
Actually we don't need any of that, let's just do this.
後ろは削除して
So we start this, And
これを開始します
at this point, TensorBoard has been started, and
TensorBoardが開始されたので
we can click there to access TensorBoard and this now shows you, of course,
クリックしてTensorBoardにアクセスできます ここに表示されています
we just ran it for ten steps, but this shows you how the loss varies.
10個の手順しか実行していませんが ここに損失の変化が表示されます
Where this is going to be useful, is when we go back and we run it on ML engine,
これが役立つのは 戻ってML Engineで実行したときです
we can also point it at a google cloud storage directory and
Google Cloud Storageディレクトリでも ポイントでき
we can watch the last function that has change during training.
トレーニング中に変化した 最後の関数を確認できます
So let's go down here and actually just stop it because
では下に移動して停止しましょう
this is just to show you that you could use it even locally.
ただローカルでも使えることを 見せたいだけなので
And it stopped 4122, so at this point,
4122で停止しました
let's go ahead and run it on the cloud, when you want to run it on the cloud,
今度はクラウド上で実行しましょう その際に重要なことがあります
there is one key thing, the data needs to be on the cloud as well.
データもクラウドに置いてください
So what I'm going to do here is that I'm going to copy
これから入力ファイルをクラウドにコピーします
the input files into the cloud, so that's basically what I'm doing,
今CSVファイルをクラウドにコピーしています
And then having done that, having copy all those files over,
ファイルのコピーがすべて終わったら
now I can submit the training job to ML engine.
トレーニングジョブを ML Engineに送信できます
So at this point, I'm submitting the training job to ML engine for many more
入力でさらに多くの手順を指定して ML Engineに送信します
and we can go back to the GCP console,
GCP Consoleに戻って
scroll down to where ML engine exits.
ML Engineがある場所まで スクロールします
Here it is, ML engine, look at the jobs and
[ML Engine]をクリックし [ジョブ]を見てください
you will see that there is now the job that is in the process of getting started.
ジョブが開始プロセスに入っています
And while the job is running you can go ahead and view the logs, and
ジョブの実行中にログと
you can see the things that are being produced by the job as it runs,
実行中に生成されるものを 確認できます
and at the end, right, you will be able to basically deploy this model.
最後にこのモデルをデプロイできます
And you'll be able to predict with it exactly the same way as we did locally
ローカルと同じように予測に使用できます
except that now this is a fully trained model,
ただし今度は 完全にトレーニングされたモデルです
it's been trained on multiple steps and it's ready to go.
複数の手順でトレーニングされ 準備が整いました
Having deployed it, we can also try predicting not just from GCloud ML engine,
デプロイしたら gcloud ml-engineで予測を試せます
but to do it the way a client program would do it.
ただしクライアントプログラムのやり方で 実行します
And the way a client program would do it is that they would basically create a JSON
クライアントプログラムのやり方は 基本的にJSONの入力を
input from some kind of Python program, and
Pythonプログラムから作成します
use this Python API to basically call the predict function and get back a response.
Python APIを使って予測関数を呼び出し レスポンスを取得します
Now, at this point we haven't actually gotten a great model, all we still have
ここではまだ優れたモデルではありません
is taking the raw data and throwing it into the model, we haven't done what we
ただ未加工データがあって モデルに入れているだけです
will do in the next course which is feature engineering to improve our model.
次のコースでは モデルを 特性エンジニアリングで改良します
And just to show you what the performance of this is,
このパフォーマンスをお見せするために
we could also train on a larger data set, it's not going to help us much,
ターゲットデータセットで トレーニングできますが あまり役に立ちません
our model isn't great, we haven't actually brought in human insight.
優れたモデルではなく 人が分析していません
You could also run cloud training on a much larger data set,
クラウドのトレーニングを もっと大きなデータセットでも実行できます
these are just running exactly the same things so I'm going to skip all this.
これらはまったく同じものを実行するので すべて省略します
But, if you have time, you want to give yourself a challenge,
時間があったら試してください
go ahead and modify your solution to the previous challenge exercise.
そして前の演習の問題の解決策を 変更してみてください
Again, I strongly encourage you to try out the challenge exercises, and
練習問題はぜひ実際に試してください
go back and discuss them on the Corsera forums, thank you
そして戻ってCourseraフォーラムで 話し合いましょう